do vegans have lower bone density more
fractures this video in the next explore
whether it's the difference in bone
density between those who eat meat and
those who don't
[Music]
osteoporosis has become a major public
health problem worldwide the morbidity
and even mortality of osteoporotic
complications such as hip fractures are
severe
osteoporosis is diagnosed by testing low
in bone mineral density and it flicks
about 1 in 20 men over age 65 and one in
four women
do we need to be concerned about bone
mineral density in vegetarians and
vegans
there are studies showing vegetarian
style diets during adolescents can have
a positive impact on bone and young
adulthood but what we really want to
know is about osteoporosis at older ages
in an earlier video I talked about
meta-analysis that concluded that
vegetarian diets particularly vegan
diets were associated with lower bone
mineral density but only by a clinically
insignificant amount given the
relationship between fracture risk and
Bone mineral density the relative risk
of fracture in vegans would only be
about 10 percent higher than a meat
eaters but that doesn't sound very
insignificant to me now I talked about
how the differences in bone marrow
density are largely just a function of
vegetarian and particularly vegans
having such low rates of obesity obese
individuals are protected from
osteoporosis because they do so much
weight bearing exercise just walking
from one room to the next basically but
we only care about bone mineral density
because we care about bone fractures
what's the comparative fracture risk in
vegetarians versus non-vegetarians now
we're talking
compared with meat eaters same risk for
vegetarians but a 30 higher risk for
vegans that was mostly wrist and arm
fractures there weren't any hip
fractures wrist fractures are among the
most common fractures and interestingly
occurs typically in women who are in
good health and active it's the kind of
fracture you get if you like trip when
you run and fall in an outstressed hand
but the 30 increased risk was after
controlling for non-dietary factors
including activities such as exercise or
an active workplace The increased risk
only disappeared when they controlled
for calcium vegans only were at higher
risk when they got under 525 milligrams
of calcium a day which is equal to the
estimated average requirement
among those getting at least 525 there
was no greater risk so the higher
fracture risk in the vegans appear to be
a consequence of inadequate calcium
intake which is essential for bone
health regardless of what kind of diet
you eat you don't need to drink milk a
greater intake of milk and dairy
products is not associated with a lower
risk of osteoporosis or hip fracture in
fact every additional cup or so of cow's
milk a day was associated with a nine
percent greater risk of hip fracture in
prospective studies but you do have to
get calcium from somewhere plant-based
sources include almonds sesame seeds
tofu calcium fortified plant milks or
the best sources dark green leafy
vegetables such as kale basically any
dark green leafies except for spinach
beet greens or charred which are just
stingy with their calcium and most
vegans in the study were getting more
than the 525. there's lots of healthy
foods packed with calcium but they only
work if you actually eat them but wait
what about the mountain of data showing
that dietary calcium intake is not
associated with risk of fractures and
there's no evidence that increasing
calcium intake prevents fractures and so
increasing calcium intake should not be
recommended for fracture prevention
but that's based on giving extra calcium
to people who are already getting enough
calcium so it might be like a plateau
effect
take women getting only 500 milligrams
of calcium a day and randomize them to
calcium supplements and you can drop hip
fracture rates 40 percent within 18
months now they also gave them vitamin D
and the women did start out seriously
deficient with vitamin D levels down
around 15. so it's hard to tease out the
effects of calcium versus the D but
vegans who aren't supplementing with D
at higher latitudes can dip down that
low during the winter months too now
there was a study in Shanghai that found
comparable bone health despite lower D
levels down around 15. they're also low
in calcium intake and still that similar
bone mineral density but given that
fracture study I'd recommend people make
sure they're getting enough calcium and
enough vitamin D but that fracture study
was published in 2007 a 2020 update
found a higher risk of fractures even in
vegans getting more than 700 milligrams
of calcium a day what explains that
we'll explore just that question next
[Music]